## **OMAR KARLSSON, PHD**

Duke University Population Research Institute

**Duke Global Health Institute** 

Omar.Karlsson@Duke.edu

https://OmarKarlsson.com

+1 857 415 8473

Ten years of research experience using econometrics, demographic methods, and GIS on surveys and demographic data. Over 30 peer-reviewed articles in medical, public health, and demography journals since 2019. Expert user of Stata. Experienced user of JavaScript (D3), Excel, R, and Python. Excellent written and verbal communication skills.

## **EXPERIENCE**

2022 - now Visiting Research Fellow

Duke University Population Research Institute

Duke Global Health Institute, USA

2022 - now Postdoctoral Fellow

Centre for Economic Demography, School of Economics and Management,

Lund University, Sweden

2019 – 2022 Takemi Research Fellow in International Health

Harvard TH Chan School of Public Health, USA

2020 – 2021 External Consultant

UNICEF, Programme Division, Nutrition Section, USA

2018 - 2019 Researcher

Centre for Economic Demography, School of Economics and Management,

Lund University, Sweden

## **EDUCATION**

2014 – 2018 PhD in Economic History

School of Economics and Management, Lund University, Sweden

Dissertation: Growth and Survival: Child Health Disparities and Early Life

Adversity in Sub-Saharan Africa

Supervisor: Martin Dribe. Assistant supervisor: Therese Nilsson

2012 – 2014 MSc in Economic Demography

School of Economics and Management, Lund University, Sweden

#### OTHER ACADEMIC EXPERIENCES

2016 – 2017 Visiting Graduate Student

Harvard TH Chan School of Public Health, USA

2013 Intern

Estonian Institute for Population Studies, Tallinn University

**2011 – 2012 Student Exchange** 

Vilnius University, Lithuania

2010 **Student Exchange** 

American University in Bulgaria

#### **SELECTED LECTURES AND SEMINARS**

- 2023 Korea University: International Symposium on Precision Public Health. *Differences in child mortality and morbidity across the first five years in low- and middle-income countries.*
- 2021 UNICEF: Nutrition Master Class. To what extent is child mortality and wasting prevalence concentrated before age two? Implications for nutrition and health programs
- 2020 Harvard Center for Population and Development Studies: Friday Luncheon Seminars. Household technology and child health

## **JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS**

Norheim OF, Chang AY, Bolongaita S, Barraza-Lloréns L, Fawole A, Gebremedhin LD, González Pier E, Jha P, Johnson E, **Karlsson O**, Kiros, M, Lewington S, Mao W, Ogbuoji O, Pate M, Sargent J, Tang X, Watkins D, Yamey G, Yip W, Jamison D & Peto R (forthcoming). Halving premature death and improving the quality of life at all ages. *The Lancet*.

**Karlsson O,** Kim R, Joe W & Subramanian SV (forthcoming). International Trends in Zinc Treatment for Diarrhea. *Pediatrics*.

Jamison DT, Summers LH, Chang AY, **Karlsson O**, Mao W, Norheim OF, Ogbuoji O, Schäferhoff M, Watkins D, Adeyi O, Alleyne G, Alwan A, Anand S, Nigatu Belachew R, Berkley S, Bertozzi S, Bolongaita S, Bundy D, ... & Yamey G (2024). Global health 2050: the road to halving premature death by mid-century. *The Lancet*, 404(10462), 1561–1614. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(24)01439-9

**Karlsson O,** Rajpal S, Johri M, Kim R & Subramanian SV (2024). Prevalence and Trends of Not Receiving a Dose of DPT-Containing Vaccine Among Children 12-35 Months: An

Analysis of 81 Low- And Middle-Income Countries. *Journal of Epidemiology and Global Health*. https://doi.org/10.1007/s44197-024-00294-6

**Karlsson O,** Benski C Kapoor M, Kim R & Subramanian SV (2024). Association between neonatal mortality and births not weighed among 400 thousand institutional deliveries in 32 low- and middle-income countries. *Journal of Public Health*. https://doi.org/10.1093/pubmed/fdae249

**Karlsson O &** De Neve J-W (2024). Washing machine ownership and girls' school attendance: A cross-sectional analysis of adolescents in 19 middle-income countries. *The Journal of Economic Inequality*, 1–21.

**Karlsson O,** Kim R & Subramanian SV (2024). Prevalence of Children Aged 6 to 23 Months Who Did Not Consume Animal Milk, Formula, or Solid or Semisolid Food During the Last 24 Hours Across Low-and Middle-Income Countries. *JAMA Network Open*, 7(2), e2355465–e2355465.

De Neve J-W, **Karlsson O**, Rai RK, Kumar S & Vollmer S (2024). Relationship between adolescent anemia and school attendance observed during a nationally representative survey in India. *Communications Medicine*, 4(1), 112.

**Karlsson O** & Subramanian SV (2023). Refrigerator ownership and child health and nutrition in low-and middle-income countries. *Global Food Security*, 37, 100698.

**Karlsson O,** Kim R, Moloney GM, Hasman A & Subramanian SV (2023). Patterns in child stunting by age: A cross-sectional study of 94 low-and middle-income countries. *Maternal & Child Nutrition*, e13537.

Subramanian SV, Khailkar A & **Karlsson O** (2023). Should India adopt a country-specific growth reference to measure undernutrition among its children? *The Lancet Regional Health - Southeast Asia*, 9. **[Comment]** 

**Karlsson O &** Dribe M (2022). Maternal height and child health and schooling in sub-Saharan Africa: Decomposition and heterogeneity. *Social Science & Medicine*, 315, [115480].

**Karlsson O.** Scarring and selection effects on children surviving elevated rates of postneonatal mortality in sub-Saharan Africa (2022). *SSM - Population Health*, 19, 101160

**Karlsson O,** Kim R, Hasman A & Subramanian SV Age Distribution of All-Cause Mortality Among Children Younger Than 5 Years in Low- and Middle-Income Countries (2022). *JAMA Network Open*, 5(5), e2212692-e2212692.

Dribe M & **Karlsson O** (2022). Inequality in early life: Social class differences in childhood mortality in southern Sweden, 1815–1967. *Economic History Review*, 75(2), 475–502.

**Karlsson O**, Kim R, Guerrero S, Hasman A & Subramanian SV (2022). Child wasting before and after age two years: A cross-sectional study of 94 countries. E *Clinical Medicine*, 46, 101353.

Subramanian SV, **Karlsson O &** Kim R (2022). Using height-adjusted stunting prevalence will fail disadvantaged children worldwide, authors reply. *The Lancet Global Health*, 10(5), e621. **[Correspondence]** 

Subramanian SV, **Karlsson O &** Kim R (2022). Revisiting the stunting metric for monitoring and evaluating nutrition policies. *The Lancet Global Health*, 10(2), e179-e180. **[Comment]** 

**Karlsson O**, Domingue BW, Kim R & Subramanian SV (2022). Estimating heritability of height without zygosity information for twins under five years in low- and middle-income countries: An application of normal finite mixture distribution models. *SSM - Population Health*, 17, 101043.

**Karlsson O,** Kim R, Hasman A & Subramanian SV (2022). Consumption of Vitamin-A-Rich Foods and Vitamin A Supplementation for Children under Two Years Old in 51 Low-and Middle-Income Countries. *Nutrients*, 14(1), 188.

**Karlsson O**, Kim R, Bogin B & Subramanian SV (2022). Maternal height-standardized prevalence of stunting in 67 low- and- middle-income countries. *Journal of Epidemiology*, 32(7), 337.

Egbewale BE, **Karlsson O &** Sudfeld CR (2022). Childhood Diarrhea Prevalence and Uptake of Oral Rehydration Solution and Zinc Treatment in Nigeria. *Children*, 9(11).

**Karlsson O**, Kim R, Sarwal R, James KS & Subramanian SV (2021). Trends in underweight, stunting, and wasting prevalence and inequality among children under three in Indian states, 1993–2016. *Scientific Reports*, 11(1), 1-11.

**Karlsson O**, Dribe M & Subramanian SV (2021). Changing speed of reduction in under-5 mortality rates over the 20th century. *Journal of Epidemiology and Community Health*, 75(1), 36-39.

Li Z, **Karlsson O**, Kim R & Subramanian SV (2021). Distribution of under-5 deaths in the neonatal, postneonatal, and childhood periods: a multicountry analysis in 64 low-and middle-income countries. *International journal for equity in health*, 20 (1), 1-11.

Thoma B, Sudharsanan N, **Karlsson O**, Joe W, Subramanian SV & De Neve J-W (2021). Children's education and parental old-age health: Evidence from a population-based, nationally representative study in India. *Population Studies*, 75(1), 51-66.

**Karlsson O,** Kim R, Joe W & Subramanian SV (2020). The relationship of household assets and amenities with child health outcomes: An exploratory cross-sectional study in India 2015–2016. *SSM-Population Health*, 10, 100513.

Kitara DL & **Karlsson O** (2020). The effects of economic stress and urbanization on driving behaviours of Boda-boda drivers and accidents in Gulu, Northern Uganda: a qualitative view of drivers. *The Pan African Medical Journal*, 36.

Subramanian SV, Chatterjee P & **Karlsson O** (2020). Lessons from COVID-19 pandemic for the child survival agenda. *Journal of Global Health*, 10(2). **[Comment]** 

Subramanian SV, **Karlsson O**, Zhang W & Kim R (2020). Geo-mapping of COVID-19 Risk Correlates Across Districts and Parliamentary Constituencies in India. *Harvard Data Science Review*, (Special Issue 1).

Teufel F, Geldsetzer P, Manne-Goehler J, **Karlsson O**, Koncz V, Deckert A, Theilmann M, Marcus ME, Ebert C, Seiglie JA, Agoudavi K, Andall-Brereton G, Gathecha G, Gurung MS, Guwatudde D, Houehanou C, Hwalla N, Kagaruki GB, Karki KB ... De Neve J-W (2020). Analysis of Attained Height and Diabetes Among 554,122 Adults Across 25 Low- and Middle-Income Countries. *Diabetes Care*, 43(10), 2403.

De Neve J-W, **Karlsson O**, Canavan CR, Chukwu A, Adu-Afarwuah S, Bukenya J, Darling AM, Harling G, Moshabela M, Killewo J ... Berhane Y (2020). Are out-of-school adolescents at higher risk of adverse health outcomes? Evidence from 9 diverse settings in sub-Saharan Africa. *Tropical Medicine & International Health*, *25*(1), 70–80.

**Karlsson O** (2019). Religion and Child Health in West and Central Africa. *Population and Development Review*, *45*(4), 707–738.

**Karlsson O,** De Neve J-W & Subramanian SV (2019). Weakening association of parental education: Analysis of child health outcomes in 43 low- and middle-income countries. *International Journal of Epidemiology, 48*(1), 83–97.

**Karlsson O,** Kim R, Joe W & Subramanian SV (2019). Socioeconomic and gender inequalities in neonatal, postneonatal and child mortality in India: A repeated cross-sectional study, 2005–2016. *Journal of Epidemiology and Community Health*, *73*(7), 660–667.

De Neve J-W, **Karlsson O**, Coetzee L, Schröder H, Subramanian SV, Bärnighausen T & Vollmer S (2018). Antiretroviral therapy coverage associated with increased co-residence between older and working-age adults in Africa. *Aids*, *32*(14), 2051–2057.

#### **SELECTED CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS**

- 2024 Consortium of Universities for Global Health 15th Annual Conference. *Life* expectancy deficits by cause of death: a life table decomposition.
- 2023 The Population Association of America 2023 Annual Meeting. *Anemia severity and school attendance among 251,401 adolescents aged 15–18 years: a nationally representative household fixed-effects study in India.*
- 2018 European Population Conference. *Influence of Disease Environment in Infancy on Childhood Health and Education in Sub-Saharan Africa*.

2015 The Union for African Population Studies 7<sup>th</sup> Africa Population Conference, South Africa. *Intergenerational transmission of Capabilities: Mothers and Children in sub-Saharan Africa*.

# **STUDENT SUPERVISION**

- 2018 Assistant Supervisor. MSc Thesis in Economic Demography from Lund University by Momoko Nishikido. *Does intimate partner violence affect contraceptive use among married women in Cambodia?* Principal Supervisor: Jeffrey Neilson. Examiner: Maria Stanfors
- 2016 Assistant Supervisor. MSc Thesis in Economic Demography from Lund University by Angelica Harryson. *The Demographic Dividend and Institutions: A Comparison between Asia and Latin America.* Principal Supervisor: Kirk Scott. Examiner: Bjorn Eriksson
- 2016 Assistant Supervisor. MSc Thesis in Economic Demography from Lund University by James Austen. Female Genital Mutilation in Senegal: The Role of Socio-Economic Risk Factors of Circumcision and Subsequent Effects of Circumcision upon Fertility and Marriage Market. Main Supervisor: Luciana Quaranta. Examiner: Martin Dribe

## **GRANTS**

2020	Swedish Research Council International Postdoc (three-year postdoctoral scholarship)
2020	Handelsbanken Wallander Scholarship (two-year postdoctoral scholarship)
2016	Handelsbanken Hedelius Scholarship. Grant for a 12-month stay at Harvard T.H. Chan School of Public Health
2015	Knut and Alice Wallenberg Foundations. Grant for the 7th African Population Conference
2013	Erasmus Placement. Grant for a 3-month internship at Tallinn University
2011	Nordplus Exchange. Grant for 10-month exchange studies at Vilnius University
2010	Erasmus Exchange. Grant for 5-month exchange studies at The American University in Bulgaria